Office of the Dean of Undergraduate Students Records, 1907-2015: Finding Aid AC136
University Archives
Office of the Dean of Undergraduate Students Records
1907-2015
University Archives
Princeton University. Office of the Dean of Undergraduate Students.
AC136
135 boxes
3 folders
6 items
1 websites
The Dean of Undergraduate Students, formerly known as the Dean of Students and the Dean of Student Affairs, is the University's administrative office charged with oversight of undergraduate residential life, extracurricular activities, and student discipline. The Dean of Undergraduate Students records contain correspondence, memos, and meeting minutes, as well as the financial records of student organizations.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
For preservation reasons, original analog and digital media may not be read or played back in the reading room. Users may visually inspect physical media but may not remove it from its enclosure. All analog audiovisual media must be digitized to preservation-quality standards prior to use. Audiovisual digitization requests are processed by an approved third-party vendor. Please note, the transfer time required can be as little as several weeks to as long as several months and there may be financial costs associated with the process. Requests should be directed through the Ask Us Form.
Scope and Contents
The records of the Office of the Dean of Undergraduate Students contain correspondence with other administrators and students, memoranda, press releases, subject files of clippings and notes, pamphlets, and brochures. Some of this material is duplicated in other University Archives collections. The records primarily document the Dean's supervision of student organizations and participation on committees; however, some files are dedicated to disciplinary infractions, athletics, or other topics which pertain to students. Prior to the creation of the office, the Dean of the College overaw these matters; therefore, some material originating from the Office of the Dean of the College was subsequently transferred to the Dean of Undergraduate Students and has been included with these records.
Please see series descriptions in contents list for additional information about individual series.
Deans of Students, Department, Tenure as Dean
William D. Lippincott, None, 1954-1968
Neil L. Rudenstine, English, 1968-1972
Adele S. Simmons, History, 1972-1977
J. Anderson Brown, Psychology, 1977-1983
Eugene Y. Lowe, Jr., Religion, 1982-1993
Janina Montero, English, 1993-2000
Kathleen Deignan, None, 1999-
Conditions Governing Access
Records of the Office of the Dean of Undergraduate Students are closed for a period of 30 years from the date of the creation of the record, with the exception of the Audiovisual Materials in Series 5, which are open for research use, and Series 6: Student Discipline files, which are closed during the lifetime of the student. Some series or folders are subject to additional restrictions beyond 30 years. These restrictions are noted in the relevant series and folder descriptions.
Series 8: Residential College Public Websites is open for research use.
Other Finding Aids
Full text searching of the archived websites is available through the Archive-It interface.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The records of the Office of the Dean of Undergraduate Students were transferred to the University Archives in multiple accessions between 1972 and 2021.
Appraisal
In the course of processing these records, two boxes of material documenting Neil Rudenstine's courses and research in the English Department were separated and removed to the Department of English Records.
Accruals
Additional transfers of records are expected from the Office of the Dean of Undergraduate Students indefinitely.
Related Materials
Several collections held by the Mudd Library contain records which relate to the Dean of Undergraduate Students. These include the Office of the President Records, the Office of the Provost Records, the Office of the Dean of the College Records, the Office of the Dean of the Chapel Records, and the Historic Subject Files. Additionally, yearly volumes of the Bric-A-Brac document the many student organizations over which the Dean of Undergraduate Students presides, and the Annual Reports to the President contain the yearly progress reports of the office.
Princeton University. Office of the Dean of Undergraduate Students.
Biographical / Historical
The Dean of Undergraduate Students, formerly known as the Dean of Students and the Dean of Student Affairs, is the University's administrative office charged with oversight of undergraduate residential life, extracurricular activities, and student discipline. The Office of the Dean of Students was established in 1954 by president Harold W. Dodds to fill the need for a dedicated administrator to supervise the social and extracurricular activities of Princeton's undergraduate student population. This decision was largely driven by the increase in undergraduate enrollment and heightened campus activity which characterized the post-war years at Princeton. Though many of the responsibilities of the newly appointed Dean of Students such as oversight of student discipline and registration of student organizations had previously been overseen by the Dean of the College, the increasing amount of time that office dedicated to issues relating to the academic curriculum necessitated a new full-time position for the extracurricular.
Since 1954 several titles have been used for the position, including Dean of Students, Dean of Student Affairs, Dean of Student Life, and in its most recent incarnation, Dean of Undergraduate Students. Despite the changes in nomenclature, the Dean's responsibilities have remained largely the same over the years. Like other Deans at Princeton, the Dean of Undergraduate Students reports directly to the President.
The first individual appointed as the Dean of Students was William d'Olier Lippincott '41 (1954-1968), who had served as Assistant to the Dean of the College since 1946. With his trademark pipe in hand, Lippincott soon became a familiar figure to the thousands of undergraduates who passed through Princeton's doors during his tenure. As Dean of Students through much of the '50s and '60s, Lippincott was forced to reconcile many of the seemingly anachronistic rules of the university with the attitudes and actions of an increasingly modern and worldly student body. Serious disciplinary infractions included the presence of females in the dormitory rooms after hours and the use of personal automobiles on campus. Student dissatisfaction with the University administration over social and political issues was a recurring problem.
On two separate occasions during Lippincott's tenure, everyday campus agitation exploded into rioting and the destruction of private and university property, the "Joe Sugar Riot" of 1957 and the "Spring Riot" of 1963. In both of these instances, the Dean of Students presided over the ensuing disciplinary proceedings. Lippincott retired in 1968 to become Executive Director of the Alumni Council, citing the need to narrow "the gap in age between the Dean and those with whom he works so closely."
Lippincott's successor was Harvard University English professor Neil Rudenstine '56. Upon arriving on campus as Dean of Students one of Rudenstine's primary goals was to develop a stronger relationship between the academic and social lives of undergraduates, however the dominant issue of his brief deanship was University involvement in the Vietnam War. On multiple occasions Rudenstine was faced with antiwar protests from sometimes hostile student groups such as Students for a Democratic Society (SDS) and in one notable incident was punched in the fracas that ensued during a demonstration. Rudenstine also weighed in on the disciplinary proceedings following the notorious "Hickel Incident" of 1970 in which the visiting Secretary of the Interior was heckled relentlessly during a speech on campus.
Additionally, as the Dean responsible for oversight of housing and extracurricular activities, Rudenstine was responsible for negotiating some of the delicate practicalities of undergraduate coeducation, which began at Princeton in 1969. Neil Rudenstine stepped down as Dean of Students in 1972, and went on to serve as Dean of the College and Provost into the early 1980s.
In 1963 a five-year term was placed upon the academic officers of the University, including the Dean of Students. While individuals could be reelected at the end of the term, the 5-year period enabled frequent evaluation and promoted the development of new ideas and fresh young administrators in the Office of the Dean of Students.
The successive terms of Adele Smith Simmons (1972-1977) and J. Anderson Brown (1977-1982) bore witness to a period of relative quiet among undergraduates, as the tumult of Vietnam dissipated and students returned to academics. An increasing international presence on campus (marked by the formation of the International Center in 1975) led to the diversification of the office's staff, and numerous programs designed to promote social interaction outside of Princeton's traditional avenues for undergrads were instituted. Notable among these was the development and implementation of the residential college system, a move sparked by the recommendations made in the 1979 Report of the Committee on Undergraduate Residential Life. The focus upon the social lives of Princeton students which characterized these initiatives was continued during the 11-year deanship of Eugene Y. Lowe, Jr. (1982-1993) and that of Janina Montero (1993-2000).
An administrative rearrangement in late 1999 brought the first major change to the Dean's responsibilities. The former Dean of Students was renamed the Dean of Undergraduate Students, and the position's oversight of student life was narrowed to focus upon the undergraduate.
From the time of its inception the position of Dean of Students has been set apart from other administrative posts by its high rate of turnover and the diversity of the individuals who have staffed it. The deanship has seen Princeton University's youngest dean, its first female dean, and its first African American dean. Many individuals who have served as Dean of Students have also been professors or lecturers at the University and have gone on to high-profile administrative positions at Princeton and other universities.
College Discipline.; College Students -- Discipline - New Jersey - Princeton.; College students -- Social conditions -- New Jersey -- Princeton.; College Students -- Societies, etc. -- New Jersey -- Princeton.; Educational counseling.; Student-administrator relationships.; Web sites.; Princeton University; Princeton University - Administration.; Princeton University. Office of the Dean of Student Affairs.; Princeton University. Office of the Dean of Student Life.; Princeton University. Office of the Dean of Students.; Lowe, Eugene Y., 1949-; Rudenstine, Neil L.; Simmons, Adele
- Series 1: Administrative, 1907-2001; 31 boxes; 2 items
  Conditions Governing Access
  Records of the Office of the Dean of Undergraduate Students are closed for a period of 30 years from the date of the creation of the record, with the exception of the Audiovisual Materials in Series 5, which are open for research use, and Series 6 Student Discipline files, which are closed during the lifetime of the student. Some series or folders are subject to additional restrictions beyond 30 years. These restrictions are noted in the relevant series descriptions and in the folder list.
  Series 8: Residential College Public Websites is open for research use.
  Scope and Contents
  The Administrative series contains general files which pertain to the activities of the Office of the Dean of Undergraduate Students. These include files on topics relating to student life, housing, and discipline, as well as correspondence with other university administrators and office staff.
  Arrangement
  The arrangement of the records at the time of transfer has been retained. Subject files are grouped chronologically and arranged alphabetically thereunder. Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by correspondent. Other records are grouped by topic.
  - Subject Files, 1907-1974; 18 boxes
    - Activism, General Articles, 1968-1969; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Accounts, 1959-1960; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Admissions, 1962-1971; 1 box
      - Admissions, 1968-1970; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Admission - Faculty Committee on, 1962-1970; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Admissions and Student Aid, 1968-1971; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Advertising Forum, 1948-1958; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Afro-American Studies Program, 1970; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Agency Council, 1960; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Association Internationale des Éstudiantes en Sciences Économiques et Commerciales, 1959-1961; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Alpha Phi Omega, 1961-1962; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - American Council of Learned Societies, 1970; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - American Field Service, 1960-1961; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - American Institute of Architects, 1952-1961; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - American Institute of Chemical Engineers, 1949-1960; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - American Institute of Electrical Engineers and Radio Engineers, 1949-1958; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - American Institute of Mining Engineers, 1950-1959; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - American Society of Civil Engineers, 1947-1960; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - American Society of Mechanical Engineers, 1948-1960; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Andover Club, 1947-1958; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Anti-War Society, 1934-1938; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Aquinas Foundation, 1947-1960; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Applications and Resumes, 1969-1971; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Argo Magazine, 1930; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Arnold Air Society, 1960-1961; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Arts at Princeton, 1959-1962; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Athletics, 1938-1974; 3 boxes
      - The Princeton Athlete, 1941; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 26)
      - Athletic Awards, 1968-1970; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 27)
      - Athletics - Players, 1968; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 28)
      - Athletic Building - Auditorium, 1963; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 29)
      - Athletic Plant and Development, 1955-1958; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 30)
      - Athletics and Athletic Eligibility, 1970; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 31)
      - Athletic Eligibility - Correspondence, Minutes, 1970; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 32)
      - Harvard - Yale - Princeton, Athletics Policies, 1954-1961; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 33)
      - Athletics - Miscellaneous, 1947-1965; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 34)
      - Trustees' Committee on Health and Economics Reports, 1951-1968; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 35)
      - Athletic Eligibility II, 1969-1970; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 36)
      - Ivy League Committee Minutes, 1971-1973; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Athletics - Ivy League, 1966-1972; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Ivy League Eligibility, 1973-1974; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Football and Basketball Issues, 1971 December; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Athletic Eligibility, 1970-1971; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Athletics - Ivy League, 1971-1972; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - Ivy Group Student Athletic Eligibility Forms, 1962-1967; 1 box
        - Class of 1966 A-E, 1962-1966, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 7)
          [restricted until 2041]
        - Class of 1966 E-K, 1962-1966, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 8)
        - Class of 1966 L-P, 1962-1966, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 9)
        - Class of 1966 P-S, 1962-1966, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 10)
        - Class of 1966 T-Z and Class of 1967 A-B, 1962-1967, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 11)
          [restricted until 2042]
        - Class of 1967 B-C, 1963-1967, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 12)
        - Class of 1967 D-H, 1963-1967, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 13)
        - Class of 1967 H-N, 1963-1967, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 14)
        - Class of 1967 N-S, 1963-1967, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 15)
        - Class of 1967 S-Z, 1963-1967, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 16)
      - Athletic Eligibility I, 1969-1970; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - Athletics, 1968; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - Athletic Committee, 1968-1970; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - Athletics - Fall Meeting, 1969; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Athletic Eligibility Lists, 1964; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - Faculty Committee on Athletic Eligibility, 1943-1969; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - Princeton Faculty Subcommittee on Athletic Eligibility, 1958-1962; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 7)
      - Athletic Ineligibility Letters, 1962-1970; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 8)
      - Behavior at Athletic Events, 1963-1964; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 9)
      - University Council on Athletics, 1962-1966; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 10)
      - University Council on Athletics, 1938-1963; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 11)
      - Princeton Athletics - General, 1958-1966; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Automobiles, 1927-1969; 1 box
      - Automobile Club, 1957; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 13)
      - Automobile Information, 1927-1969; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 14)
      - Automobile Regulation - Parking Information, 1962-1967; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Band, 1947-1961; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Baptist Students, 1951-1960; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Barn Dance Club, 1961; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Basic Engineering Society, 1948-1961; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Behavior at Athletic Events, 1967; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Belfry Magazine, 1948-1949; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Bicker, 1966-1967; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Biographical Information, 1966-1969; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Princeton Liberal Society, 1961; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Black Awareness, Committee on, 1970; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Black Faculty, 1970; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Black Students, 1968-1970; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Black Students, 1969-1970; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Black Students, 1970-1971; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Black Studies, 1969; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Black Writers, Newspaper Editorial, 1968 November 18; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Bomb Threat, 1970; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Boston College, 1969; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Bric-a-Brac, 1966; 2 folders (Box 3, Folder 34-35)
    - Bric-a-Brac, 1950-1966; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Bric-a-Brac, 1943-1955; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Bridge Club, 1933-1961; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Brink (Student Peace Union), 1961; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Brown Hall I, 1969; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Brown Hall II, 1969; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - The Princeton Calendar, 1947-1949; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Camera Club, 1938-1960; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Campus Fund Drive, 1952-1965; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Cap and Gown Club, 1955-1969; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Central Dormitory Council, 1969-1970; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Chancellor Green Student Center, 1954-1967; 1 box
      - Chancellor Green Student Center, 1955-1961; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 9)
      - Chancellor Green Student Center, 1962-1967; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 10)
      - Chancellor Green Student Center - Finances, 1954-1957; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 11)
      - Chancellor Green Student Center - Finances, 1960-1961; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Chapel Choir, 1930-1962; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Chapel Deacons, 1957-1966; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Chapel Rule Clippings, etc, 1946-1964; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Charter Flight Material, 1962-1963; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Cheerleaders, 1952-1961; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Chemistry Club, 1948-1958; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Chess Club, 1961; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Chest X-ray, 1960-1962; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Chinese Students' Association, 1962; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Choate Alumni Club, 1947-1954; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Christian Science Organization, 1947-1961; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Christian Science (Medical Exemptions), 1959-1960; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Cincinnati Club, 1948; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - University and City Education Schools, 1968; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Chicago Club, 1947-1956; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - The Chimera Magazine, 1942-1943; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - The Clapper, 1963-1964; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Chinne and Beake, 1964-1965; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Class Day, 1965; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Class of, 1965; 1961-1965; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Class of, 1966; 1962-1966; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Class of, 1967; 1963-1967; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Class of, 1968; 1964-1968; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Class of, 1969; 1965-1969; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - Class of, 1970; 1966-1970; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - Class of, 1971; 1967-1971; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Class of, 1972; 1968-1972; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Class of, 1973; 1969-1973; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - Class of, 1974; 1970-1974; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - Classic Film Club, 1957-1965; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - Classical Drama Club, 1964 October; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - Cleveland Club, 1950-1958; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - Clubs, 1932-1970; 3 boxes
      - Joint Interclub Committee - Minutes of Meetings, 1962-1968; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 45)
      - Joint Interclub Committee, 1963-1970; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 46)
      - Club Managers or Stewards, 1966-1967; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 47)
      - Rate Men, 1938-1966; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 48)
      - Rate Men and Section Sizes, 1964-1966; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 49)
      - Rates and Finances, 1943-1966; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 50)
      - Reports on Gentleman's Agreement, 1960-1967; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 51)
      - Undergraduate Interclub Committee Meetings, 1964-1965; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 52)
      - Residents and Presidents, 1941-1965; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 53)
      - Clubs, 1949-1970; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - Inter-Club Council, 1968-1969; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - Campus Club, 1953-1969; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - Cannon Club, 1957-1969; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 4)
      - Central Committee on Clubs, 1940-1967; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 5)
      - Chaperone's Letters, 1963; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 6)
      - Charter Club, 1960-1970; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 7)
      - Colonial Club, 1950-1969; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 8)
      - Cottage Club, 1957-1968; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 9)
      - Cloister Inn, 1957-1970; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 10)
      - Dial Lodge, 1957-1970; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 11)
      - Elm Club, 1953-1970; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 12)
      - Club Membership, 1964-1965; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 13)
      - Gentleman's Agreements, 1964-1970; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 14)
      - Gentleman's Agreement, 1932-1970; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 15)
      - Graduate Boards, 1960-1968; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 16)
      - Graduate Interclub Council, 1933-1968; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 17)
      - Inter-Club Committee - Minutes, 1964-1967; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 18)
      - Inter-Club Committee, 1964-1970; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 19)
      - Ivy Club, 1959-1968; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 20)
      - Terrace Club, 1953-1970; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 21)
      - Tiger Inn, 1961-1968; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 22)